"What Is GLP-1 and How Do GLP-1 Agonist Drugs
(Like Ozempic) Work?"
Even over just
the last decade or so,
obesity rates have
spiraled out of control.
Are GLP-1 receptor activators
the long-sought-after panacea
for obesity?
Well, first of all,
what is GLP-1?
The gastrointestinal tract
is known
as the largest hormone-secreting
gland in the human body,
releasing more than 20
peptide hormones.
About 1 out of every 100 cells
lining our entire digestive
tract acts as a nutrient sensor
and can secrete hormones
accordingly,
including GLP-1,
glucagon-like peptide-1.
The primary stimuli
for GLP-1 secretion
are meals rich in fats
and carbohydrates,
and the main action of GLP-1 is
to signal nutritional abundance
to the brain,
reducing our appetite
so we don’t eat
too many doughnuts.
GLP-1 also slows things down,
allowing us more time to digest,
and the slowing of the rate
at which food leaves our stomach
helps with blood sugar control
after a meal.
So, GLP-1 hormone-mimicking
drugs were actually
first developed to treat
type 2 diabetes.
The reason you can’t just
give people GLP-1 directly
is because it’s broken down
so quickly,
it hardly even makes it
one time around the circulation,
thanks to inactivation
by an enzyme in our body.
But then,
a compound was discovered
that activates GLP-1 activity
but was resistant
to enzyme breakdown.
And it was found in a lizard.
It’s a constituent
of Gila Monster venom.
And the first drug was born.
Using that as a template,
the first GLP-1 agonist
was created
and approved
for the treatment of diabetes
about 20 years ago.
Instead of half lasting
2.5 minutes in the body,
it lasted about 2.5 hours,
but still had to be injected
twice a day.
Then came liraglutide,
which lasts all day,
but even once-a-day injections
can be a pain.
Enter semaglutide,
branded as Ozempic,
which could be injected
just once a week.
It was approved to treat
diabetes in 2017.
Within a few years, a daily oral
version had been developed,
again for diabetes,
but researchers running
those clinical trials
noticed a surprising
side effect:
people’s appetites diminished.
Indeed, if you drip the hormone
GLP-1 into people’s veins,
it reduces their appetite,
leading
to decreased food intake.
And not just a little.
We’re talking about
a decrease in caloric intake
by as much as 25 to 50 percent.
The GLP-1 hormone not only
slows stomach emptying--
so you feel fuller longer
after eating--
but also works
as an appetite suppressant
by triggering
parts of the brain
responsible
for hunger and cravings.
GLP-1-secreting cells don’t
only line our intestines;
they’re also in our brains.
So, GLP-1 agonist drugs,
meaning GLP-1-mimicking drugs,
work kind of like
the way birth control pills do.
Birth control pills mimic
placental hormones,
thereby tricking our body
into thinking we’re pregnant
all the time.
Ozempic-type drugs mimic GLP-1,
thereby tricking our body
into thinking
we’re eating all the time;
so, it dials down
our hunger drive.
In 2021, semaglutide,
originally approved as Ozempic
to treat diabetes,
was rebranded at a higher dose
as Wegovy to treat obesity,
and the weight-loss industry
changed overnight,
shifting away
from meal replacements
and portion-control plans
to the new world
of private equity-funded
telemedicine entities
set up to offer these
injectable weight-loss drugs.
Even Weight Watchers has openly
embraced these kinds of drugs
as the future of weight loss.
They were even approved
for kids as young as age 12--
tweens, not even teens.
Is that a good idea?
What are the pros and cons
of these new
weight-loss medications?
That’s just what I’ll cover
next.